<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An humble letter of loyalty to the Londoners admonishing them of their immiuent [sic] miseries, and advising them to a timely prevention. / By L.T. a well-willer to the welfare of the King, Parliament, and kingdome.</title>
            <author>L. T.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94923</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T24</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.6[118]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212624</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871227</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871227</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160978</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94923)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160978)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 245:669f6[118])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An humble letter of loyalty to the Londoners admonishing them of their immiuent [sic] miseries, and advising them to a timely prevention. / By L.T. a well-willer to the welfare of the King, Parliament, and kingdome.</title>
                  <author>L. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeer 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>With engraved border.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 11".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:160978:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An humble Letter of Loyalty to the Londoners:
Admoniſhing them of their immiuent miſeries, and adviſing them
to a timely Prevention.</head>
            <byline>By L. T. a well-willer to the welfare of the KING, Parliament, and Kingdome.</byline>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE imminent dangers and preſſing calamities of this Kingdome are notoriouſly known to all, and to ſome by ſad and wofull
experience, who have already taſted of that bitter cup of miſery, of which we muſt all drink the dregs, except GOD in
mercy prevent, and give us hearts to make uſe of the means which he hath put into our hands: our Religion bleeds, our
Lawes, Liberties and Priviledges are languiſhing at the laſt gaſp, this all men know, this all men fear, of this every man talks
and diſcourſes, and this is all they do to prevent and recover theſe almoſt irrecoverable wounds: This generall deluge
and flood of miſery, wherein the particular welfare of every man is like to be drowned, (as every man well knows) is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
the ſubject of our diſcourſe, which ſhould be the onely object of our imployments to remedy: we ſee our ſelves deeply
plunged into a deep ditch of diſtreſſe, and all that we doe is to crie (God help us) hath not GOD in great mercy given us
an Army, Men, Ammunition and Money, what is wanting that can be deſired, but only active hearts and hands to make uſe of theſe bleſſings,
which I pray God to grant unto us, otherwiſe theſe which ſhould be the means of our ſupport, will prove the inſtruments of our greater down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall,
and who may we thank but our own dull and drowſie ſelves? Rouze up your ſelves then you noble Citizens of LONDON, you that have
been hitherto the chief and great Patriot to the whole Kingdome, who are not to be parallelled in your great and liberall Contributions, and in
your forwardneſſe in all actions tending to the ſupport and recovery of this oppreſſed Nation: my humble advice unto you is, that you perſevere
in this your good beginning, that you crown the work with your conſtant and unwearied reſolutions, that (now at this time of need) according
to your late Proteſtation, you put in practice all juſt and honourable wayes, for the preſervation of your Religion, Lawes, Liberties and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,
which (together with your lives) are in immergent danger. Loſe not the honour you have got by your good beginning: ſhould you now
prove faint-hearted or negligent, would not the burden of that ſpeech of our Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 28. fall flat upon your renowned City, to the
perpetuall diſgrace of it? That when a man having begun a worke, and through want of adviſed forecaſt, or diligent proſecution, is
not able to finiſh the ſame, he becomes a reproach to all that heare it. The eys of the whole Kingdome are fixed upon you, ſuch as are in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe,
and in the hands of cruell enemies expecting aſſiſtance from you, and from whence els ſhould they expect it, but from your Magazine of
ſtrength? O let not their juſt expectations fail them at their need; ſome are reſolved to live and die in your aſſiſtance, let not your remiſneſſe
prove a diſcouragement to them: and others there are who daily expect and plot your ruine: O let your diligent wiſdomes prevent that: Be
not ſo overtaken and puſſed with your own private affaires, which can be no way advantagious when the publike goes to wrack. Can the City
flouriſh when the Countrey decayes? if the Countreys be deſolated, how long I pray you will the City ſubſiſt? But you may ſay you have
done your parts, you have freely contributed of your eſtates, you have ſet forth men horſe, arms, all ammunition and proviſion for the defence and
preſervation of the Kingdome: this cannot but be confeſt and acknowledged to your perpetuall honour. 'Tis true, God hath bleſt you with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities,
and nothing is wanting, neither money, munition, nor men, neither do your men want courage: but why then doth the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer
thus go on, deſtroying and making havock without controul? or why do not theſe means raiſed by you prove the inſtruments of defence
and preſervation to the Kingdome? You complain that you ſuſpect that things are not rightly carried in the managing of theſe means, you ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
(and that not without grounds) that there are falſe brethren and trecherous Counſellours in the Army, you ſuppoſe that many of your
Commanders are ſuch as aim at their own particular gains, more then at the publike weal, and therefore deſire rather to protract and prolong the
war, then to diſpatch and put a period to it: thoſe things you fear (and certainly not without cauſe:) but why then do you not by your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms
ſearch and ſift out the matter, by your humble deſires and petitions to the high Court of Parliament, and to his Excellency the Earl of <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex,</hi>
who are always moſt ready and willing to hear and redreſſe ſuch things as ſhall appear to be amiſſe, eſpecially ſuch matters of great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
I do not preſume to propoſe any way for the proſecuting of this particular, but do leave it by you to be conſidered of, but being a matter
of ſuch high concernment, whereon the welfare of the Nation doth depend, let it not be by any means neglected: neglect rather your private
occaſions for a while, and apply your ſelves to the publike affairs. What will it avail you to be getting by your trades, when in the mean time
through your too much ſecurity or negligence you are made meer bondſlaves, and the eſtates you have taken ſo much pains for ſhall be ſpoiled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
your faces, and taken away by villains and raſcals. Nay what hopes can you have of any thing but loſſes by your trading, ſo long as thoſe
wicked ſpoilers and robbers are abroad, robbing and ſpoiling your Countrey-Chapmen, in whoſe hands you truſt your eſtates. Me thinks there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
it were better policy rather to ſecure what you already have, then by a covetous deſire of more, to hazzard the loſſe of all. Me thinks it is
ſtrange, that a buſineſſe of ſuch importance (as this muſt needs be) ſhould be ſo much feared, ſo much talked of, and no courſe taken for prevention;
will you give your money to become ſlaves? will you willingly and wittingly be undone? can you ſuffer your ſelves and your poſterity to be thus
betraid? But you will ſay, there is at this time a Treaty on foot, and you have hopes of peace, which with truth I pray God to grant (our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
is if it were poſſible to have peace with all men:) But it is feared this Treaty (if there be any) will prove as a ſmall calm or breathing time
between two ſtorms, that the latter may be more grievous and vehement then the former. Had we an abſolute peace and quietneſſe amongſt us;
it were good policy to have our <hi>Pax armata,</hi> our peace in every reſpect provided for war, much more in theſe trecherous and dangerous times. Is
not the cauſe juſt and honourable? what do we ſtand for, but the glory of God in the purity of Religion? the honour of our King, in reſcuing
him out of the hands of evill Counſellours, deſperate Cavaliers and cruell robbers, our own juſt Liberties and Priviledges? the leaſt whereof de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves
our utmoſt indeavours to maintain. Let us then ſpeedily put in execution all poſſible means to defend it according to its deſerts. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
the reſolution of a heathen, <hi>Emori per virtutem mihi praeſtat, quàm per dedecus vivere:</hi> it is better to die honourably in defence of an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
cauſe, then to live in diſgrace. I might multiply motives upon you to this purpoſe, but will not tire your patience nor my own with theſe
abrupt lines. Remember the words of wiſe King <hi>Salomon,</hi> with which I conclude, Be circumſpect and diligent inmannaging of theſe great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires,
<hi>Prov.</hi> 5. 9, 10, 11, 12. leſt thou give thine honour unto others, and thy yeers unto the cruell: leſt ſtrangers be filled with thy wealth, and
thy labours be in the houſe of a ſtranger, and thou mourn at laſt when thy fleſh and thy body are conſumed, and ſay, How have I hated inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and my heart deſpiſed reproof?</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed in the Yeer 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
